Logical operators involve using the keywords
and, or, and not to compare two or more conditions
and then return a true or false.
As with many types of operators, the order
of operations plays a factor in a result,
as we will see in an upcoming example.
For this code example, 143-logical, we have
a tuple that shows some gases in the periodic
table of elements on line 1.
On lines 2 and 3, we have variables storing
the number of gases and the number of liquids
in the table.
On lines five and seven, we have print statements
with logical keywords in use.
Let’s analyze the statement on line 5.
Look for the and keyword and then test the
logic of the conditions on either side of
the keyword.
Is sodium in gases?
No.
Right away, this statement is false because
for an and statement to be true, both parts
of it need to be true.
I will run this code, and indeed this statement
is false.
Before we move on to the next print statement,
let’s add the word not in front of the in
keyword.
Sodium is not a gas, so this part of the statement
is true.
Let’s analyze the other part of the statement.
There are fewer liquids than gases, so this
expression is also true, and when I rerun
the code, the statement is indeed true.
Let’s now analyze the print statement on
line 7.
Is hydrogen a gas?
Yes.
Helium is also a gas, but this statement would
be true anyway because, in an or situation,
only one side of the expression needs to be
true for the or statement to be true.
Next, we see an and statement, and the number
of liquids is not 4, so this should be false.
Yet, when I run this code, this statement
is true.
Why is that?
To know why this statement returns true, we
need to understand the order of operations
as it pertains to logical statements.
Not is always evaluated first.
Then, and is evaluated before not.
Thus, we evaluated the statement left to right
in this case, but this part, helium in gases
and number of liquids equaling 4, was evaluated
first.
That part is false.
But then, when you evaluate this with hydrogen
being a gas, the statement as a whole becomes
true because hydrogen is a gas.
And, what did we say about an or statement?
Only one side of the statement needs to be
true for the whole statement to be true.
As we will see in the upcoming topic on arithmetic,
adding parentheses to any part of a statement
can dramatically affect the results of said
statement.
I will wrap parentheses around the two gases.
What do you think the result will be now?
This part is true, but the whole expression
compared to this and statement should return
false because this part is false.
And, in rerunning the code, the statement
as a whole indeed is false.
Besides learning about logical operators,
we have seen the importance of order of operations
and how parentheses can shape the logic of
a statement.
Not knowing these factors leads to logical
errors and lots of frustration as to why code
seemingly does not work, even though technically,
it does work.